[开场音乐]
收音检查1, 2...1, 2, 3, 4...敏捷的棕色狐狸跳过了懒狗...
Check 1,2 Check 1,2 1,2,3,4 The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog
这里是React播客，我是小钱
This is react podcast I'm chantastic
今天我们逆溯时光，回到React的起源
today we're going back, way back, back to the beginning of react
10年以后的今天回顾React的发展
10 years in the rear view mirror it may
感觉React的成功似乎是注定的
feel like react was always going to
毕竟这是一个由Facebook推出的明星框架，光环加身，似乎不可能失败
succeed did a framework by Facebook was too big to fail but this isn't that kind
但今天的故事会告诉你事情并没有那么简单
of story in fact there were many times
事实上在React发展历程的很多时间点，这个框架都看起来要失败
in reacts history where it seemed like it wasn't going to succeed at all
所以10年间到底发生了什么，让React从被人嫌弃到大受欢迎
so what happened how did react go in 10 years from looking Dead on Arrival to
乃至成为今天居于统治地位的JavaScript框架
becoming the dominant front-end JavaScript framework that it is today
故事要从2011年的Facebook讲起
it starts at Facebook in 2011
JQuery和backbone.js在前端领域正如日中天
jQuery and backbone are dominating front-end
但是更富有自己独特哲学的工具，比如Ember.js, AngularJS, Knockout.js已经出道
JavaScript but more opinionated tools like Ember angular knockout are already on the scene
在技术宅之外的世界中，《江南Style》刚被上传到Youtube
In the outside world Gangnam Style has just been uploaded to
《Call me maybe》是第一热歌
YouTube Call Me Maybe is topping the charts and the freshest meme is the
当时最新的迷因是过于黏人的女朋友
overly attached girlfriend in Internet
也就是说按照互联网纪年，从React诞生到现在，一个永恒已经过去了
years it's basically been an eternity
那么让我们系好安全带，打开勿扰模式，观赏下面这个精彩的的菜狗逆袭故事
so strap in set yourself away enable that do not disturb because this is quite the Underdog Story
[音乐]
我发现这个摄像机有个红色提示灯，这个没有
I think this camera has a red light, but this one doesn't
[Applause]
[Music]
把这个挂在衣服上就行
just keep it on with this
收音测试1, 2...
testing one two testing
[Music]
foreign
当拿到Facebook offer的时候我非常激动，我兴奋地告诉了妈妈
work at Facebook I told my mom I was like really excited The Social Network
当时《社交网络》这部电影刚刚上映，她看过电影后非常不鼓励我进入Facebook工作
the movie had just come out and she had you know seen it recently and she was actively discouraging me from joining
她的理由是扎克伯格看起来不是一个好孩子
because she was like Mark Zuckerberg doesn't seem like a very nice boy
我还在那工作的那段时间，Facebook是有点特别的，那种特别是一去不返了
Facebook in the time I was there was I don't think they'll be anything like it ever again it was certainly not like
可以确定的是当时的Facebook和我此前工作的任何一家公司都不一样
anything that I had experienced before
我加入Facebook几个月以后，侃爷拜访了Facebook园区
in fact just a couple months after I joined Kanye West came to visit
他爬上了食堂的桌子，现场rap了一段
Facebook's campus and he got up on a table in the cafe and you know wrapped a
我当时试图向一个刚刚毕业的同事解释，
few bars and I was working mostly with this guy who had just graduated from
我在这个行业工作了10多年，这种事情从来没有发生过,
college and I was trying to explain to him you know I've worked these crap jobs in software at that point had been like
像这样的事情从来没有在软件工程师行业发生过
10 or 15 years nothing like this ever happens not to software Engineers you're
[侃爷rap中]
my stressing your mama sues Mama say
Mama say Mama Don the son
JavsScript当时正经历一场对自身存在意义的怀疑
JavaScript at the time I think was going through this little bit of an existential crisis as to
比如说它是不是一门真正的编程语言
whether it was like a real programming language
还是说仅仅是一门玩具语言
or a toy programming language and so
所以当时有很多发展的趋势
there was a lot of churn so you had
JQuery, mootools都很流行
jQuery was popular and moo tools was
有很多受欢迎的框架激烈竞争市场份额
popular and there was so many different like warring Frameworks to try to get
这些工具之间有很多相似性，也各有其擅长的场景
the Mind share and there's a lot of similarities between them but each one had its kind of bespoke differences and
但是它们中间没有一个在构造复杂用户界面和应用时表现特别突出
none of them were actually really fantastic for building really kind of complicated user interfaces and apps
当时的趋势是应用越来越复杂，需要做的事情也越来越多
there was this trend towards more sophisticated applications that do more
当时在Facebook我们的主要技术栈依然是服务端渲染
stuff and at Facebook we still had a primarily sort of server rendered technology stack which
因为很长一段时间内，我们都致力于减小不断增大的前端应用中的JavsScript产物体积
um you know one of the things that we fought against for a really long time was just growing JavaScript bundle sizes
而这是因为当我们在浏览器中实现越来越多的功能以后，前端应用变得越来越慢
so as we moved more and more stuff to the client the client got slower and
也就是说当时我们一直在往CSR-SSR这个天平的SSR端靠近，尽量减少客户端JavaScript体积
slower so we actually swung the pendulum towards server-side rendering and towards you know minimal amounts of JavaScript for a while and there was
当时的感觉是我们知道浏览器端的开发模式已经不能满足新的需求
this feeling that we knew that what we were doing for client-side development
但是我们同时感到服务端技术也不能彻底解决问题
wasn't working but also that server side wasn't going to get us all the way there
这差不多就是React诞生前的技术环境
so I think that was the kind of environment that react came out of
2010年加入Facebook之前，我做了很多开源工作，特别是在JavsScript领域
I joined Facebook back in 2010 I've been doing a lot of Open Source work particularly in the JavaScript world I
我曾经是dojo.js toolkit委员会成员，
was a committer on the dojo.js toolkit back in the day which is one of the the
dojo.js，jQuery和prototype都是JavaScript运动的先声
granddaddies of the JavaScript movement along with prototype and jQuery
我在Facebook的头两年都在移动团队
I spent my first two years of Facebook on the mobile team
当时我们已经开始着力和Apple以及Google的竞争
we had started off a big push to compete with Apple and Google and we thought
我们认为我们最大的机会在于直接投入web领域
that our best chance of success as a company was to go directly to the web
着力于建设HTML5生态
and really push to build out the HTML5
作为战略的一部分，我和另外两位工程师Vladimir和Bailey
ecosystem so as part of that we developed myself two other Engineers called Vladimir
创建了一个叫做Bolt.js的JS框架，叫这个名字是因为我们
khalestikov and will Bailey built a framework called bolt JS so named
将几项我们几个喜欢的技术整合固定在一起，形成了这个框架
because we bolted together a bunch of things that each of us liked
（bolt做动词有"用螺丝固定"的意思）
Bolt.js基本上是Facebook对客户端MVC架构的一种实现
bolt was basically more or less Facebook's implementation of a client's
对比当时的一些MVC框架比如Backbone.js，我认为Bolt.js可能是一种更好的MVC实现
head MVC I think it was like a pretty good version maybe a better version of things like backbone and a couple of other Frameworks that had existed at the
但是它带有Facebook业务特有的一些限制
time but it was born from a place of the specific constraints of Facebook
"它将是你Facebook体验的核心"
it's the heart of your Facebook experience
"经过彻底的重新思考"
completely rethought from the ground up
“和一年的精心打磨”
we've been working on it all year
"它就是Timeline(时间线功能)"
and we're calling it timeline
Facebook属于第一批体验重于其他一切的产品
Facebook was one of the first big products that was really an experience more than anything else
你不会用Facebook来买日用品或者买票
you're not trying to buy groceries or get tickets or anything like that on
用户只是想上去找点乐子
Facebook you really just want to be entertained and as such you know the
因此它的用户界面需要让人愉悦
user interface itself needs to be really
Bolt.js不是一系列分散工具的集合
pleasing bolt was not a tool belt it was
而是一个真正的应用开发框架，它被设计用来构建复杂，有丰富交互的应用
truly a application development framework something designed and meant to build complicated interactive rich
事实上，它也确实被当时的Facebook用来开发非常复杂的真实世界应用
apps and was being used to build pretty complicated very real products at Facebook at the time
最后的发展是我们基本上需要用Bolt.js来重构Facebook的大部分应用
we ended up having to essentially replicate most of Facebook
不管是时间线，聊天，还是新闻流，以及整个相册应用
all the various apps be it timeline chat news feed we had a whole photos app that
整个团队快速扩张
we built and so obviously the team had to expand greatly like that so I think
在某个时刻团队大概有25个工程师，有的做bolt本身的开发，有的做基于bolt的应用开发
at some point we probably had maybe 25 Engineers working on all this between building bold and building apps built on
这还仅限于移动团队
Bold and that's just on the mobile team
Bolt从来就不是问题所在，有问题的是当时应用开发的架构
bolt was never the problem it was the architecture that would eventually break
当时的架构是压倒骆驼的最后一根稻草
down for us as the the product itself
随着产品逐渐复杂和团队人数的增多，
got more complex and as we added more Engineers to the team we didn't hit a
变更产品功能变得越来越困难
wall but it started to get really really hard to make changes and so you know
这时候广告团队的Jordan对现状发出了疑问:
that was around the time that Jordan was on the ads team and he's like I wonder
"难道没有更好的开发方式吗?"
there's got to be a better way
[谁是Jordan Walke?]
不是这个
Jordan是一个谜一样的人物
Jordan is an enigmatic figure he uh he's a
他行事隐秘，我对他所知不多
little secretive so there's not much that I know about him
Jordan和我一直没有特别进入公共视野，特别是Jordan，
从React的早期开始他就远离了关注的焦点
Jordan and I aren't necessarily we haven't necessarily been in the spotlight much especially Jordan kind of shied away from spotlights since the early days
Jordan当时是广告团队的一名工程师
Jordan was a product engineer at the time working on ads and ads has one of
广告在当时是横跨Facebook所有业务中UI最为复杂的
the most complicated pieces of UI across all of Facebook at the moment
在应用复杂性方面，当时的广告团队正在逼近没有React框架时所能做到的极限
on the as team they were hitting much you know really hitting the limits of what you can do without react uh
当时的开发者已经很难把屏幕上的UI和对应的代码联系起来，并理解代码的作用
complexity wise and just the developers ability to hold in their head and understand a bit of code that somebody else wrote and you know look at the screen and say okay this code is doing that and I need to know why
Jordan有很多有趣的想法，比如对于Blot的函数式使用
and Jordan had a lot of very interesting ideas around how you could take what we had done in both and make it much more functional
如何让Blot更容易地规模化应用，以便让人更容易理解大型应用
and make it more um ability to make it easier for it to scale with, people's ability to understand large
所以我们有很多持续进行的讨论
applications and so we had a lot of ongoing dialogue and he would come back
我们会来来回回探讨可以如何改变Blot
and forth to us with various ideas how to change it
我记得React早期的名字其中一直就是FBlot，意思是函数式Blot
I think one of the original names for react was F bolt which is functional Bolt
[音乐]
Jordan意识到有一种更容易的方式，可以解决Blot中的一些棘手问题
to do it to solve some of the tricky Parts in bolts in an easier way so what
所以Jordan的思路是（至少他是这么告诉我的）
Jordan decided to do or at least the story that he had told me was
不管应用中发生了什么改变，
不管是API状态变动，还是用户输入了什么，我们都销毁掉所有UI，然后重新渲染一切
hey wouldn't it be easier if any time anything happened in the app API State changes user type something we just blow away the entire UI and we re-render all of it
对比当时的框架，那时流行的是数据双向绑定
if you look at what every other framework was doing at the time it was called two-way data binding and this was
但Jordan说忘记数据绑定吧，我们不再操心那个了
not that it was like forget about data binding we're not going to do that at all
新的做法是任何时刻发生任何变动，我们都重新渲染整个UI
anytime anything changes we're just going to re-render
当然旁边有个注脚，我们不会真的重新渲染整个UI，并且我们会尽可能少地重新渲染
and then there's an asterisk which says well we're not going to remember everything we're going to try to render
但是概念上，我们不会再手动维护视图和模型之间的关系
as little as possible but conceptually we're not going to manage these relationships between views and models
概念上我们会...(直接销毁之前的视图，并根据新的数据状态生成新的视图)
we're just gonna
坦白说，我那时觉得这是一个疯狂的想法，而且当时我也对框架持怀疑态度
honestly I thought it was completely crazy at the time I was really down on
我觉得这个想法不会成功
Frameworks in general and I thought there was no way that was going to work
对于很多人来说Jordan的想法过于魔法，超出了他们对于现实的认知
to many people that seemed like magic it was so far outside of everybody's idea of how things should work and do work
(我们花费了)很多精力去说服他们
that um yeah it took a lot of commenting
[Music]
我已经在Facebook工作10年了
I've been working at Facebook for 10 years now
曾经我和一个叫Jordan Walke的人碰过面
I met this person called Jordan walk
背景是有人告诉我Jordan有一个关于JS的有趣项目，我可能会对其感兴趣
some people told me like he had an interesting project about JavaScript and I may be interested and so I had this
所以我和他约了一个会，在会议的开始他问了我一个问题：
meeting with him and uh one thing he asked me at the beginning of the meeting
“前端开发目前最困难的事情是什么？”
was what is the most difficult thing to do in the front end right now and I mean I was six months out of
我那时刚毕业6个月，我说我不知道，他告诉我是“(UI的)更新”
school I was like I don't know and the thing he told me is updates you need to
你需要找到要更新的dom节点，选择合适的事件后增加/移除事件回调等等这些
find the dumb node that is going to change you need to like change the listener to like the Click event and like remove it and like do all of this
整个过程相当繁琐，Facebook广告业务代码的大量bug都在这个过程中产生
which is like pretty complicated and then this was also like a massive source of bugs within the Facebook adbase
我被他说服了，承认道“好吧这大概是最困难的事情”，然后他说他有一个解决方案
I was like okay yeah you're right like this is probably like the hardest thing and it was like I have a solution for this
(我听了他的方案以后)觉得这家伙的想法太疯狂，不会成功，也不会有好的性能表现
I was like okay this guy is crazy like this is never going towards never going to be performance
会议结束过了几个星期我就忘记了这件事
the meeting ended for like a few weeks I forgot about the idea
但是有一个周末我重新考虑了这件事，觉得自己也许应该尝试一下
but uh one weekend I was like okay maybe I should try this like maybe there's something to it
[Music]
加入Facebook之前，我做过一个魔兽世界工会的搜索项目
before joining Facebook I walked on a way to find your guilds in World of
我们需要在20000个工会中搜索到目标
Warcraft and we basically need to search through like 20 000 yields and I did
我做了很多的性能优化工作，以便用户更改搜索过滤条件时能更快给出搜索结果
like a lot of uh performance work to like be the fastest way to display possible when you change all of those filters into this real time
我当时想我花了数月的时间全职优化这个项目
and I was like okay I spent like months full time like working on like making this super
现在让我试一下用React重写会有什么不同
performance let's try it with react and in practice uh it took me like half an
我花了差不多半个小时重写了项目，重写的版本性能不如原版
hour to write it and it was actually like not as performant but like around
但是和原版相差不远，我被结果震惊了
the same order of magnitude as performance and I was like mind blown
从那以后，我就成了React的头号粉丝
and to this day I became like the biggest react fan in the world I was in
之后我在相册团队的所有工作时间我都在使用React，并且尝试在自己的项目上使用
the photos team and like spending all of my working hours like trying to like use
同时也在向其他人布道React，因为我感觉React会改变世界
react on my own project in the photos team evangelizing I felt like it could change the world
它也确实改变了世界
which it did
[Music]
Jordan的项目现在开始逐步取得进展，其他人也开始参与进来
Jordan is making Headway on his project he's gotten others involved and they're seeing the value but not everyone is
但不是所有人都买账，其中一个Facebook的经理认为Jordan的项目分散了员工的精力
impressed one manager started to take notice but saw Jordan's project is a
所以他们让Byron和Jordan会面，告诉他项目需要终止distraction so the athlete Byron to meet with Jordan and put a stop to it
一见面我就知道这次会面会很尴尬奇怪
we get into a room instantly I knew that this was going to be weird
因为我们的态度明显不同，我的态度是我需要理解你的项目到底价值在哪
because we showed up with very different energies so I'm showing up with this like okay Jordan I want to understand what's going on with your
我需要确定它值得长期投入和能带来长远价值，可以解决我们面临的问题
project but I also want to help make sure that we are spending our time well and we're working on things that are gonna have longevity and solving problems we
Jordan却非常兴奋地想给我展示他的demo，推销该项目具有的激动人心的特性
want to have and Jordan came in with like can I show you a demo of what I've been working on like this is so exciting and it does this and it does that and
接近会面尾声的时候我不得不承认我被说服了，他的项目确实有点东西
eventually like towards the end of this meeting with him I had to kind of admit like he had something really compelled like I was now really interested in
我开始希望了解更多的项目细节
learning more about what what he was doing
Jordan最后也表示只有该项目最终会被人们使用的前提下，他才会继续开发下去
so Jordan's pitch to me was like I only want to invest in this and work on it if it's going to be something that
如果管理层决定这不可能，他当然不会继续投入开发，但是他也表示对项目充满了信心
people will use and if that's not going to be the case like sure we're not going to do this he's like but I feel really strongly that all the ways we've been
他认为截至当前所有的UI开发方式都有缺憾
doing UI development up until now have been flawed whether they're a JavaScript
不管是现存的可以完成很多工作的JS框架还是其他久经考验的UI开发模式
library that doesn't quite work for us or whether it's like a 30 year old uh tried and true model for doing UI application development like they all
都受困于同一类基础问题，也就是状态管理
suffer from the same base problem Estate Management
他认为自己的方式(React的前身)是下一步的正确方向
and I think this is the way forward and Lee if you could just like dig into
他说如果你能花点时间再了解尝试一下，然后我们再见面讨论，也许我们会有更清晰的答案
the code and learn more and try it and then come back and we'll talk about this again um then we can figure this out it's like
我说好的好的，于是我研究了他的代码
all right all right and so I did I dug around the code and it was um
一开始发现有点难懂，但是我最终学会了怎么使用
a little hard to understand uh but I eventually got to play with it got to
我用它做了几个小东西，然后总结发现，确实这里有非常有意思的东西
build a couple of things and uh like had to admit coming away that like yes there was something incredibly interesting there and that was how I got sucked into
我就这样成了项目的一员，接下来好几个月都在做相关工作
the project I ended up working on it quite a bit for the the next couple of
Byron给项目带来了一种生机勃勃的设计思维
months Lee brings us like rigor and sort of design mentality to these things that
他帮助React初始的几个版本做了标准化
um really helped with the initial versions of react in terms of standardizing it
将React从一个Facebook的内部项目变成了一个外部世界可以欣赏接受的东西
and turning it from something that was kind of like an ugly baby that it just uh grown up at Facebook to something that really people could approach from around the world
[Music]
当我开始尝试理解React代码库和使用它构建应用的时候，立刻就遇到了几个问题
there were a couple of problems that I faced right away when trying to understand the code base and build something
它所使用的一套工具和思维模型和我之前作为UI工程师接触到的完全不同
Not only was the the set of tools and the mental models really different from what I was used to as a
而且语法，概念，一整套术语都很特别
UI engineer the syntax and the programming just like Concepts involved just the terminology was also really different my takeaway
虽然它的卖点是会让UI开发更简单，但是我却不禁感到使用它非常复杂
was you know okay the whole bid here was that this would be simpler but I can't help but feel like this is really complicated
出于让自己理解它的目的，也是希望能够帮助理清一些概念
mostly as a as a desire for me to understand the model um but also with a hope that it would kind of end up helping resolve some things I
我开始建立一个术语表，将项目涉及的概念一一梳理出来
wanted to build uh like a glossary like what are all the things the concepts and
并确定与其对应的动作行为
then what are all the like actions or like verbs that are going on here and so
我拿着列出的一个个术语去找到Jordan和其他项目组成员，验证相关概念的理解
I I literally just like listed them all out and then I would go back to Jordan I'd go back to other people working on it and ask questions like did I get this
他们会说“对的”“不对”“你想错了，应该这样考虑”等等
right are these definitions right and they go yeah okay no you should really think about it that way and be like okay well that's not how this and it would go
经过多次讨论，我们对概念的理解开始趋于一致
back and forth and back and forth and I'd be honing these definitions and
并且意识到有些概念是重复的，它们应该叫同一个名字
along the way we'd realize like oh this concept and that concept are the same we're going to name them one thing instead of two things
最终经过重新思考的，用新术语描述的组件生命周期出炉了，也就是面向用户的React API经过了一轮重构
so unwinding all of this and essentially writing up what ended up being like a reimagining of the component life cycle and therefore sort of the entire front-facing API for react
项目组成员对这样的变化非常欢迎，我也很高兴
and I was very happy to see like incredible enthusiasm around that Jordan
Jordan说这太棒了，真的帮助理清了概念
was like oh this is amazing this really clarifies the ideas at that point a
那个时候一些其他成员开始加入项目组
handful of other folks had gotten involved with the project too and then I
接下来几个月我都在一点点地完善这些概念，帮助人们理解，在这个过程中极大改变了面向用户的React API
spent sort of the next month or so sort of piece by piece folding those into place and pretty significantly changing the surface API of react in the process
我认为这是React思想的第一次真正传播，它从一个Jordan脑海里的东西变成了一个被整个团队共享的理论
that was I think the first shift from this being a thing that existed mostly in Jordan's head that other people were playing with to a thing that all of a sudden felt owned by the whole team uh
这里说的团队就是受项目愿景吸引的一帮Facebook UI工程师
where team here is like a collection of UI Engineers scattered across Facebook who were sort of bought in on this
现在有了统一的术语以后，如果有人有问题，任何人都可以跳出来回答而不用再仅仅依靠Jordan解答
Vision who now felt that like we now have the same terminology we can use when someone has a question anyone can jump in and answer it rather than only
这就是React思想的第一次传播
Jordan that was the first big shift
[Music]
最开始使用React的几个项目之一是UFI: 统一反馈界面
one of the first projects um that Greg was used for was the ufi the universal feedback interface which
基本上就是每篇贴文下面的喜欢/评论/分享功能
is basically the likes comments and shares at the bottom of each post this
当时还处于Facebook称雄的网络时代，Facebook是连接人群的一大驱动力
was still during Facebook's kind of web era when Facebook on the web was like the sort of Big Driver of Engagement
新闻流功能每天使用的人超过10亿
news feed had a billion people hitting it every day
因此经过了大规模的性能优化
and was massively tuned for performance
用户界面的输入和输出都要求高度的互动
heavily interactive surface both on the input side of course you're like
输入侧有点击喜欢按钮，聊天框中输入内容等
clicking it to add likes you're typing into it to add comments but also on the
输出侧我们希望评论可以实时显示而不需要刷新
receiving side we want comments to come in live so as you're looking at it as a
也就是你盯着网页的时候新的评论会嗖地自己上屏
comment comes in we want it to just pop up right there and there was this
也就是希望用户界面可以表现地像聊天窗口一样即时更新
product desire for that interface to feel almost like a one-off chat thread
当时这种想法非常让人激动
and that was so cool at that time and as
当这个想法被实现以后，人们又想如果一篇贴文可以做到这样，那么对于整个贴文界面是不是也可以做到
that started to work the second thread was well okay if this can work for this really isolated sense of messaging then what if it could work for messaging as a whole
而这又是一项复杂且容易出bug的工作
and this was another really complicated and fraught with bug surface area that
这催生出了React中的一些新想法，JSX语法诞生了，一些如何管理数据的想法出现了
was when a lot of the ideas in react congealed the jsx syntax was introduced and some of the ideas about how to work with data and react sort of were clarified
一些UI工程师和消息团队成员，特别是我们的领头人Jing Chen意识到
a couple of our UI Engineers along with the messaging team if I remember correctly Jing Chen was sort of the champion of this project realized
除了React我们还需要一种全新的方式去思考"状态"
that we needed a completely new way to think about State too
so my name is John
um and I'm a software engineer and the
product infrastructure team at Facebook
is an application architecture designed
around react's principle of
unidirectional data flow paired with
flux react could go beyond the view
layer to model entire applications this
shift in how to think about State paired
very well with how react was thinking
about updating UI and ended up being
sort of the next chapter for how to
think about react being more than just
how do you model complicated UI but how
do you model sufficiently complicated
applications like this was something
that expanded the full screen and
multiple touch points and had navigation
to it and it allowed us to step into
that next chapter I remember asking Jing
like hey how's it going with this react
stuff you know do you think this is
going to work she's like yeah this is
pretty good I'm pretty sure it's gonna
work that was when I became more
convinced
[Music]
thank you
Instagram joined Facebook in 2012. I
think we had started calling it react by
then and there was a couple Engineers
from Facebook that went to join
Instagram to help them expand the
product offering at the time Instagram
was just an iOS and an Android app and
they wanted to have a web presence as
well
foreign
[Music]
11 years in San Francisco it was a
really fun made a lot of great friends
but the the change of pace out in the in
the countryside is is great
um it's just very peaceful and nice
I went to Facebook straight at school I
studied computer science undergrad and I
got a master's degree Facebook was
believe it or not the like cool place to
work back in 2010 it was like this great
product that like everybody used it was
super cool on college campuses and I was
really excited to work there
foreign
I joined Facebook video
the pitch was we're the third largest
video site in the world after YouTube
and Dailymotion I think and there was
like one engineer working on it and like
you get to be engineer number two and I
was like that sounds pretty cool we
worked really closely with the iOS
photos team in the Android Photos team
and we were building an Instagram killer
and nobody remembers this but it was
called Facebook Camera
one morning the photo scene got called
into the office early they said like be
at HQ at 8am and then the VP of
engineering was like hey we bought
Instagram they're your new co-workers
now and these were like our people that
they were like our Fierce competitors
you know we looked at them a little bit
as the enemy I'm sure they looked at us
a little bit as the enemy they were a
really small team at the time they had
their core fundamentals really nailed
but there was a lot of stuff they needed
to figure out that they did not have the
team to figure out along with their own
and a big one of those was what does it
mean for Instagram to be on the web the
web experience is really important for
driving growth and so this was a pretty
important priority and so me and this
Designer Michael lumens started building
all the web stuff and that's kind of
where react
enters the pictures when we started
developing this website
[Music]
we were given this mandate to use client
rendering so I went to the product
infrastructure team at Facebook
which was run by like Tom Aquino product
infrastructure's role was to support any
team that needed help
and do it in a way that you know your
key indicators of success are going to
be other teams saying yeah that really
helped us you go to them and you kind of
consult the Council of Elders and they
they give you their recommendation and I
said hey we need to do client rendering
what do we do and the recommendation at
the time was yeah we don't know we've
got like three different things that
we're working on you should go try one
we had uh something called bolt Js
there was a second thing called jshtml
and then there was this this thing
called react
you wouldn't spoke to Jordan about using
react and he came and talked to me about
potentially using both for it but I
think he really really liked Jordan's
ideas around functional programming the
conceptual model of react was like crazy
Innovative and it really really spoke to
me my background was in distributed
systems I was not somebody that loved
front end or thought front end was like
doing things well so the fact that react
came in with like a totally Fresh
Approach and like didn't really care too
much about existing best practices like
I was I was on board with that so while
I had evaluated all three I really just
dove in on react to build a prototype
first and that ended up shipping on
instagram.com which was the second use
of of reactant production ever and the
first use of building a full application
end to end in react
when I chose react for Instagram
it was not well known within Facebook
and it was this like kind of crazy
science experiment
not even close by the time Instagram was
and you know Pete was started playing
with it uh it was significantly better
than it was in the early early stage uh
but it still needed a ton of iteration
we had to take this thing that was very
much tied to Facebook's infrastructure
which back then was a big giant PHP
application and I had to go get that
working in a Django application which is
a totally different system and what was
key was not doing that once but making
that a repeatable process and and making
sure that that pipeline didn't break I
think he hit a number of really
interesting problems along the way which
quite proved the fact that react was not
quite ready for that scale and along the
way Pete and the team that he was
working with into that building a lot of
really interesting things
[Music]
foreign
some of these products ended up being
fairly successful there were relatively
short time to to deliver a relatively
high quality product that show that this
model could work and it was not just
that but people liked developing using
it and so that kind of spread and took
off and especially if you got more and
more investment they came clear that
this was
what we wanted to use and it was really
ads that was kind of using Baltimore it
had a higher level investment more
people working in that code base that
already knew it and more components
so it was a harder shift to make
the ads team just before I joined ads
from the mobile team had done a full
rewrite of the ads creation flow into
bolt which took them I think upwards of
six months replacing a very old PHP
application with what time was
considered a very modern JavaScript
application but at the same time react
was also now actually deployed for real
on Facebook and had a team that was
forming around it so we now had two
viable Frameworks that were both live on
Facebook both solving real problems we
shouldn't have two especially two that
were similar similar enough to confuse
people like if you looked at a code
their code almost looked identical but
that worked really differently it would
actually be an absolute nightmare if you
had to work in both so we had to decide
which which to use
[Music]
a lot of this was ended up being a
conversation between myself and Jordan
we did an evaluation of boredom a lot of
performance-based stuff and trying to
figure out where the edge cases were on
the pro side of react obviously there's
all the things that we know now it
handles complexity way way more even
when writing the as creation flow in
bold we had already hit one place that
you just could not do in Bolt without
writing spaghetti code and you can do in
react so we knew in the future even if
it was only 10 of the experiences we
were building we're going to run into
this problem again now it might only be
10 unmaintainable but as you scale that
across a company that is growing rapidly
this becomes an absolute mess the cons
of it on the other hand were that react
in a lot of ways was not battle tested
yet there's a lot of things that simply
didn't work in react it couldn't handle
forms they'd never done a text box and
there's a lot of complexities around
handing awkward form controls like radio
buttons and so on that it messed up just
performance issues where it would try
and re-render large blocks so they
hadn't had to do all of the performance
improvements that obviously exist now on
the organizational side that the other
con was that we had just done the
six-month rewrite in both
um Facebook had done an IPO recently and
the stock had
since IPO
Facebook wasn't making enough money and
so the ads team is the team that makes
you know that's where the money starts
if we stop for four months we're gonna
have to tell everybody
sorry no money for you so there was a
lot of conversation back and forth about
all this it was got very difficult
initially a lot of the engineers that
used bolt including Shane realized just
what you said like look we've invested
so much in this thing and it's it's
really worked for all this stuff
certainly we can work through the next
set of challenges we're having so
initially there was opposition to react
coming in and saying like how are you
gonna you know this new thing that's not
even proven yet this is our business
this is really important when Jordan and
I were working through it was definitely
uh some emotions uh there
um and mostly I think it came from uh
each of us having a lack of context of
where the other one was coming from so I
think there was a lot of talking past
each other in the end Mike shroffer
stepped in and said look
make the right technical decision make
the right long-term decision
and whatever it is
you know I'll back you up but if you
need to pause product development for
four months you can we all kind of just
got in rooms and you know worked through
all these things and got everything out
in the air of you know what's a
technical problem what's an organization
problem what's a financial problem uh
and uh kind of a
computer understanding eventually
um through uh
through uh with lots and lots of coffee
that the react was the right way to go
but um it was not a straight line at all
he ultimately was one of the biggest
proponents of decision makers and ads
switching all over everything to react
and that doesn't happen in most
companies and most companies if that's
your baby project you try to undermine
the other the the upstart because you're
you know you're really defensive over
your own thing that was not the vibe at
Facebook at the time and I think that
Shane in particular really
exemplified that
there was still a lot of work to do on
the ads creation flow tensions were
mounting and the team was stuck here
again to get them unstuck is Jing Chen
we'd have this thorny management issue
and a lot of people disagreeing with
each other up and down the management
chain on both sides of you know in ads
and in this product infrastructure group
those building react and we'd send Jing
in to talk to the engineers and everyone
come out like patting each other on the
back full agreement a plan to move
forward so she's great at building a
consensus because she's able to drill
into the important technical details
identify them really quickly and and get
everyone talking about the same thing
she obviously helped both build the
product but she also made sure that
every time we found a bug in react or
just something that didn't handle yet
she either stepped back from products
and then just fixed the framework or she
went back to the team and said look we
need two or three Engineers working on
this stuff for the next month to unblock
the ads team the ads manager was
complicated enough that it actually
ended up being a really great source of
um performance improvements and finding
like where are the true points where it
does doesn't quite scale so I think it
was a lot of like you using the building
blocks that we had
and as you start to assemble them into a
really complicated looking application
what are the new problems that come out
of that way that we need to solve and
there was definitely a lot of those this
is one of the most fun intense periods
of my career as I remember it we would
be going to meet with the team and we
would have to help them put some feature
in and we would code it up ourselves
first and react just to make sure that
the that they wouldn't hit any rough
edges or more like to find all the rough
edges that we knew they'd hit and figure
out what the solutions would be so it
was really exciting because we were
working on two things at the same time
one was delivering this really
complicated really important software
project for Facebook uh the ads manager
and the other was refining this
framework that we really believed in uh
which was react
by the time we had rebuilt the ads
creation flow which I think took about
four months it had been battle tested
with basically everything about the
browser supports all the form fields and
everything and also massive performance
issues that had been resolved so at that
point it was kind of felt that it was
ready to be open source because
you know we we used it in multiple
different types of contexts and that uh
you know um it would actually be
generally useful to the public
[Music]
where's
uh there is not
sorry open sourcing reactor is never a
question for me that was the goal
from the very beginning Tom had this
idea he called it project perception
and he was really
angry I think it's probably the best
word for he's angry that Facebook was
hiring all these luminaries from the
JavaScript World they would come to
Facebook and you know because we
discouraged people from writing
client-side JavaScript and because it
was a hard environment to maneuver in it
would actually go pick up mobile because
that was where a lot of the interesting
client-side development was happening
and Tom was determined to change us
around I remember going to this
conference and someone like I was
talking to someone and I told them I
worked at Facebook on JavaScript and
they're like why would you do that I
hate what Facebook does to the
JavaScript industry you have hired all
these really great people from these
really great projects and we have no
idea what they're working on now they've
given nothing back so I think when react
came along I started very early on
talking about if this thing works for us
I really want us to find a path to open
source and I was running that up the
like management chain like very early so
when the time came to open source it
there were some meetings it was
controversial
but we had all the support we needed
already
the process of open sourcing uh is
interesting there's first a technical
problem to solve you have to figure out
how to extract it out of your
infrastructure and make it work in the
open source which is all the homework
that we did for Instagram
we made this call that like we will not
impact developer productivity at all
it's going to be entirely on the open
source team which was just a bunch of
people that wanted to open source it to
make it work then actually pulling the
trigger on open source
we had to write a lot of documentation
we spent actually a lot of time with the
documentation to explain like hey what
is react what are all the concepts and
we try to put ourselves in the shoes of
like somebody that want to build an app
how do we give the documentation in a
way it like helps them do that polish
Channel as they did a lot of this
because he really had the experience
with what the ecosystem needed to make
this work at the time Apollo fantasy was
a huge force on open sourcing as was
James Pierce who was the head of
Facebook open source James had joined
the company and he really wanted to
change Facebook's open source image we
had previously open sourced a lot of
stuff but we let it rot we would say hey
we're an open source company here's our
great framework and then we would just
never maintain it and James and Paul in
particular were like pretty instrumental
in saying hey if we're going to open
source react we're going to do it right
internally there was a lot of excitement
because we had already been using this
thing for a while and it was working for
us we were excited about it
we chose jsconf us which was kind of the
I don't know the Oscars of JavaScript is
that fair representation maybe you know
all the celebrities are there and
everyone's paying attention and
everybody watches it live on YouTube Tom
and Jordan put together this
presentation Tom is a great speaker and
Jordan is a brilliant engineer it was
like Lennon and McCartney type of
situation there was no way that this
thing could possibly fail
[Music]
it was in Florida
um at like 9 00 a.m We were in Menlo
Park and we woke up early we took the
first bus into the office it was
completely empty and we're like getting
ready to like press the button on the
repo to open sources Jordan and I were
all excited we got up on stage I'm going
to talk a bit about how we do JavaScript
application development at Facebook it
was a little unconventional I like did a
little bit of it he did more of it so
along with react we are shipping an
embeddable XML syntax and we're calling
that jsx and we jumped into showing some
code and that code looked different it
looked weird here we have react used
with jsx and people were rightfully
skeptical we'll call it everyone hated
it everyone thought it was awful
foreign
[Music]
ly we were expecting a much better
reception or at least an oh that's
interesting exception we thought there'd
be some language nerds in there who
would um think oh I can do fully
functional program in the UI oh at least
that's interesting it was a really
humbling experience it was kind of a
letdown for us because we had worked
nights and weekends on getting this
thing open sourceable and then when we
go to launch it everyone hated it the
thing that everyone focuses on is that
people really hated jsx
I haven't watched this video in a while
see these divs are not
exactly what you're used to they're not
Dom nodes
so they're special reactives and I'll
get to why that's important I don't
remember thinking that they were hating
it I don't remember at all thinking that
they were like tweeting a bunch of a
bunch of stuff this is the slide for
sure we haven't talked about any
problems we're trying to solve we
haven't talked about why this is working
for us or what were the principles of
design we're just like boom here's some
XML in your JavaScript and people are
like hey what is happening
uh poor Jordan
what we didn't really fully understand
was how big of a Delta there was between
where the rest of the world was in the
JavaScript community and where Facebook
was
I don't blame them I don't think anybody
who tweeted Facebook is crazy
was crazy themselves I think they were
they were kind of right we were a little
crazy
I think there was a moment for me
personally where I felt like
you know my goal with the open sourcing
of this was to get us closer to the
community and I may have set us back a
step I may have demonstrated that we
actually have no idea what we're doing
because what we're doing is so much
different than what the rest of the
community was doing and internally there
was a
well we messed that up we made the wrong
call
um because I think the measure of
success would have been wow Facebook
engineering is doing some really cool
stuff and instead it was Facebook
engineering has no idea what they're
doing I think that gsconf
um appearance might have been Jordan's
last conference for a good few years I
think camokino didn't go back for a
while as well it turned into a bit of a
troll Fest for no good reason and
particularly for something that was as
an Innovative and useful and you know
just fantastic for developer
productivity and just it's literally a
gift to everybody here here move faster
for free to have people misunderstand it
and say all these bad things about it
that were just
you know knee-jerk reactions without
actually having taken time to think
about it
um can only must have felt very bad
especially because both Jordan and Tamil
had already gone through all this
internally in Facebook for two years but
inside in Facebook it's a smaller scale
you can just get in a meeting room and
talk about it
um but you can't really do that with the
whole world can you there were some
technical decisions that were made as
hard to react that were self-evident
within Facebook but were like crazy when
when um given to a different audience in
the community so there was this notion
of separation of concerns at the time
like you didn't you shouldn't put your
HTML CSS and JavaScript into the same
file like should I really extract them
out and you should like uh like have
this separation and so this was like
very like the best practice at the time
what was interesting about the approach
to separation concerns in react is that
you separate your concerns into
different components so rather than
saying I have my view concerns over here
and my model concerns over here you say
you have your news feed concerns over
here your photo concerns over here your
admin panel concerns over here so it's a
different way of separating concerns and
so there was like a lot of backlash
around like oh those people at Facebook
are clowns like they don't know how to
write software and everything we thought
that react probably had no future
outside of Facebook
[Music]
it looked like all hope was lost for our
friends at the Facebook office but
fortunately someone outside of Facebook
was willing to give it a chance
foreign
[Music]
started using react in 2013 it was not
popular in the community it had just
been announced at jsconf
I saw the announcement post on Hacker
News and immediately
thought that it would be helpful for one
of the projects that I was working on at
the time I was building an interactive
math question editor at Khan Academy and
it was something that had a very
component oriented architecture I was
trying to use backbone.js at the time
and found that the state management was
getting a little bit hard and when I
looked at react I thought to myself wow
this actually looks like it solves a lot
of the problems that I have right now
I'm looking at this post from 2013 that
I guess I wrote a week after I learned
about react and it was right after I had
started trying to use it and somebody
had asked how is Facebook's react
JavaScript library and I was a few days
into using it and so I decided to write
an answer to that question based on my
experience
the answer I wrote is very
positive I think I was having a really
good time using it and it was solving my
needs really well one line from the post
says I just rewrote a 2000 line project
in react and have now made a handful of
pull requests to react everything about
react I've seen so far seems really well
thought out and I am proud to be the
first non-facebook production user of
react and I talked a little bit more
about some of the technical details and
how it was helping me it's cool to look
back and it's almost a bit of a time
capsule to see how even one week into
react being released I was already
pretty excited about it and I think that
excitement lasted for a long time
I converted my entire code base that I
was working on at the time over to react
I think it ended up being less code and
it was easier to understand and it was
faster pretty quickly I said Okay I want
to keep using react and I ended up
deploying that to production my my
Rewritten code and that was I think the
first production code using react
outside of Facebook
foreign
it was a brand new project that had just
been open sourced and not many people
had used it before and so there were a
bunch of rough edges it seemed like you
know maybe nobody had tried to use it in
a particular way before or if something
just wasn't documented well enough and I
was trying to use it a slightly
different way than it was intended I ran
into these little bugs or issues where
it didn't work quite as I was expecting
it to for some of those I read through
the source code and tried to figure out
okay why isn't this working is there
anything that I can be doing differently
for other cases I ended up joining the
IRC chat Channel where a lot of the core
team members were hanging out after it
had been open sourced
that helped me get started not just
using react but also starting to
contribute to it as I started filing
issues and helping other people who were
in that chat room as well as starting to
make small code changes and starting to
improve react over time her perspective
from you know Khan Academy and just
being outside of Facebook was so
valuable so helpful so if he started as
someone using react externally
then sort of like moved on to being
someone who contributed to react core
externally then became the most
significant contributor to react core
then we would have these like weekly
team meetings and invite Sophie to come
and so Sophie like worked out with her
local manager at her company to like
carve out Friday afternoons to come to
Facebook and hang out with us and so
determined not to do what we had done
previously where we hired folks from the
open source community and then they
never contributed anything back she
became like the the first ever like open
source recruited member of the team
Sophie's involvement lifted the spirits
of the react team it also got them
thinking that maybe just maybe the rest
of the ecosystem had just misreact
unfairly they had something special they
knew it what they didn't know was how to
convince everyone else
I think there are people on the team
like me and Jordan and Tom and
christadeau who like the The Challenge
and the the competitive nature of it we
knew that this was good technology and I
was so sure of that that um
you know I viewed it as just a a
messaging problem you know okay we gotta
crack how we message this to people
because they don't get it and we have to
figure out how to how to bring them
there
the open source feels like a milestone
and it feels like this is the end my
impressive is just the beginning because
when you open social actually have zero
users now you need to actually like
build a community uh get all of the bug
fixed like make sure it actually solves
the use case for the people and so this
is like when the Journey Begins we
buckle down we and we we also realized I
think that really when you have a
project like this that's
um different you have to convince people
one by one
so I think that's really what we focused
on
and we learned a lot doing that we
learned that
the ideas in reactor are solid but
really the ideas are not what people
encounter when they adopt a framework
what they encounter are the docs and the
error messages what they need more than
anything else when they adopt something
is an incremental way of doing that
so the team got to work they focused on
spreading the knowledge of react one
concept at a time one person at a time
then an opportunity arose
another conference
later the same year thank goodness Pete
gave a talk at jsconf EU I had my desk
over by the um by the product
infrastructure team I was sitting next
to Tomo and he's like oh we're just like
sponsoring this JS conf EU conference
and like we have to give a keynote and
like I don't want to give it because I
think he was like he didn't want to go
through all that stuff because you know
after you give the talk like people go
and yell at you after you get off stage
and you go to the happy hour and stuff
it's like it's not not the most Pleasant
thing in the world and I was like I'll
do it
um I'll take the free trip to Berlin and
go uh give a talk at a conference hey
I'm Pete uh I'm gonna talk to you about
a library for creating user interfaces
that we call react
and we open source this at jsconfus a
couple months ago and we got some kind
of sarcastic responses on Twitter
a little bit of snickering that kind of
thing
um we weren't really communicating what
we were doing
um so I'd like to talk to you today
about the design decisions
um around react uh what we're doing
differently than other Frameworks and
kind of the implementation that lets us
make these decisions and make it really
fast
for this talk it was like here's what
makes react different I'm not even
trying to say it's good I'm not even
trying to say you should use it I'm
trying to say that this is interesting
and there's a lot of interesting stuff
about how this thing works that you
should pay attention to
and
um that really resonated with people and
so we got these kind of early innovators
you know if you think of the crossing
the chasm
diagram where you've got your your early
adopters and then you've got your
laggers and in the middle you have your
kind of normal companies that talk
really got those early adopters fired up
and evangelized and react inside of
their own companies after Pete's talk
interest started to pick up people
started paying attention they just
wanted to you know let me let me just
see if there's something there and so we
got this kind of like Slow Burn of
adoption of react and it prompted some
really interesting conversations it
recruited Brandon Bloom into the
community who came from the functional
programming World somewhere he started
talking to his friends and said hey I
think this like react thing is actually
worth paying attention to and then he
goes and talks to his friend David Nolan
who is this very well known very well
respected really great musician and
JavaScript developer I think he was
working at the New York Times at the
time and I was passing through New York
to do something and it grabbed coffee
and I asked Pete some questions and
Brandon Brandon Bloom that was my friend
that said you should really look at
react and the reason I was excited about
it more than I think you could have been
if you were JavaScript developer
JavaScript is kind of multi-paradigm you
can do object oriented you can do
functional if you want but it's not
required but in closure enclosure script
functional is the most idiomatic thing
and nothing existed like we were sort of
like always trying to get things to work
but it was always felt like there was
friction I was like
still early in my career right and this
is like really senior super smart
engineer and it was the type of thing
where like he would ask me questions
about it and I would like stumble to
explain it and I would explain it poorly
and then he would repeat it back to me
in like a super eloquent great way and I
was like yes I'm gonna steal that and so
when I sat with Brandon and Pete it was
like this huge light bulb went off I was
like finally this is so Random uh
Facebook made this functional UI
framework Eureka I mean it was
definitely a Eureka moment it it did
allow closure script programmers to
finally write a reasonably performant
functional uis and it was very natural
it was a very very good fit like a week
or two later he wrote this blog post
called the future of JavaScript mvcs
that just like changed the trajectory of
the project
in many ways you look at react and
you're like there's no way this could be
fast there's no way it could be
efficient and then I showed like you
know these diagrams of what um backbone
and react ohm look like and react is
much better especially when you're using
persistent data structures so my article
I think was focusing purely on the
technical benefits of the design it
removed The Superficial consideration
and I think people started saying okay I
will try it not I'm going to use it but
it removed that I'm never going to use
that too oh I'll give it a shot this is
interesting once that post came out like
within three months after that I would
say that we were one of the big
contenders if you were picking a
JavaScript framework if you want to
spread an idea you need to really
convince a few people
and have those people share your message
you can't just be shouting at yourself
more people started to realize that
react
some good ideas and made UI development
simpler in a lot of ways over the course
of the next I would say like year or two
we're kind of just tracking things like
you know like Google Alerts of how many
times is it being mentioned who's
writing about it what projects are
cropping up
um because react was very unopinionated
about a lot of stuff that you need in
order to build a front-end web
application and you know people would
fill in the blanks and there was a bunch
of State Management libraries that
cropped up and there was a bunch of you
know router libraries that cropped up
and server-side rendering strategies and
so there was this sort of Slow Burn of
adoption over the next year or two react
is a small focused UI library but it
proved capable when tackling Facebook's
hardest problems in other big companies
noticed
but there was one company especially
eager to rethink best practices
[Music]
we first heard about react back in 2014
the Netflix website had been built using
Java web uh it was very slow it took
about 15 minutes to get up a build and
we decided to move to a more modern
framework there we go now at the time we
weren't quite sure if you know this
react thing was going to work out it was
kind of new and so we were very
apprehensive especially since we were
building the future of the next 10 years
of the website right you know we make a
bad choice now we got to backtrack
um you know years worth of work and so
we were very careful about you're not
jumping into something that was too
bleeding edge
and so what they did was they actually
pitted two teams against each other each
was given 30 days to build a prototype
with one being react and the other one
being backbone and after 30 days the
choice was clear
so thank you all for coming out tonight
we're really excited to have you here
and share the learnings that we've had
building the new UI in react for the
past year
it was not this stage it was our next
stage over where I gave my react
presentation back I guess in 2015.
same feeling like oh my goodness I've
got to convince all these people that
react is amazing
um but I guess it worked so as part of
the team that built the new site using
react at first it was very clunky like
you're writing components and they're
not quite you know you're putting too
much logic into them or you're thinking
too big it's not clear the difference in
the Paradigm and then you start to use
it and you go okay wait wait wait I'm
thinking much more Atomic hence the
symbol of react I'm thinking about this
in individual reusability okay now I'm
thinking about the testability of these
components I'm seeing the benefits now
come out of it I can reuse this over
here we can test this over here we can
change this here we can add props in
here and it becomes very exciting to see
that new paradigm come to play and go
this is going to be revolutionary this
is going to change the world let's go
back in time one year to the old Netflix
UI you guys might remember this one the
overall look and feel is kind of like
this old DVD kind of box art feel and so
I actually want to show you one of the
early prototypes of what we thought the
new UI would look like we knew that
going forward the world was changing web
was changed changing things were moving
faster and our competition was moving
faster as well so choosing react and
going with a more modern framework
really helped us accelerate how fast we
could build the website how fast we
could get new changes that door how fast
we could try improvements for our
customers to make the best possible
experience
and because of that we've been at the
Forefront of leading what UI design
looks like in terms of web development
we've had a lot of companies copy us
which we take is a great compliment but
we were there first because of react and
its ability to move so quickly in terms
of design
this is how it ended up turning out and
this is a UI that's big and immersive
and completely built in react so we're
very very proud of it and the result
[Music]
Netflix was now praising react publicly
and with a second big company betting
big on react the framework grew in
popularity in fact it kind of took on a
life of its own and the community
started to take off
[Music]
react at this point was getting more
popular
and somebody on Twitter mentioned like
hey it would be cool to have like a
react conference and a lot of people
started like uh commenting and tweeting
and everything about this and uh I went
to my manager tomokino and he was like
there's like 50 tweets about react today
like people are talking about organizing
conferences should we organize a
conference and I was like I don't know
what that means I don't know how to do
that but like maybe I was very post
doing a conference um I thought it was
very cool that we got so much traction
without really pouring marketing money
into it even though react came from big
tech company Juggernaut Facebook it was
a small group of people that were like
really dedicated to seeing this thing
succeed so it felt like this very Indie
you know Rebel Alliance type of project
and so I was like we don't need a user
conference like with like we got this
Cool vibe going on like let's see how
far we can push it I was totally wrong
we had said to ourselves I think it
would be fun to host a react conference
but are there even enough people using
react who would want to go to that and
eventually we decided Well let's try it
let's try to host the conference and see
how it goes
within a minutes all of the tickets were
sold out and we actually crashed the
website that we are handled for like the
actual payment system and everything
trap the CTO of Facebook actually like
reach out to me saying like hey I have
this very important like VP or CTO or
like of some company that one scene that
couldn't get in like hey can you do as a
favor and I was like I would love to
like kill the CTO and everything but
like you know like we're like completely
booked certainly we were very surprised
about how quickly the tickets had sold
out we didn't realize just how much the
react ecosystem had grown and just how
much enthusiasm had been created by
early adopters
foreign
[Music]
quickly as far as conference planning
goes and we just had it on campus in one
of our cafes and we you know bus people
from the nearest hotel and it was very
very under produced
um but it worked out really really well
good morning everyone
and welcome to react Jessica
the conference when they're like
extremely extremely well as the
organizer of the conference I'm so
excited to be here and we open source
like a bunch of our projects like so
react native and we started talking
about graphql about three day and so
yeah it's been a massive success there
is this moment where you go and you see
the stage and it's like there's a giant
wood
cut out like logo of the react atom and
I was like my friend Michael the
designer at Instagram drew that in front
of me like in the middle of the night
before we were going to open sources
thing because we needed a logo and I was
like Michael just like throw something
together real quick and like now it's
this thing that has somebody has built a
giant sign with this on it and there's
something about the physical impact of
that that's really cool that was the
moment when it dawned on me that react
was becoming something different
you know so for a long time what react
was to me was a software project
and the reason why I wanted people to
adopt it was because I really thought it
would make their software better and
make their lives better and make their
on-call rotations better there are a lot
of reasons why I thought it would help
them
after that conference what I realized is
that react was becoming a community
there was meetups that would happen the
immediate next week that would have an
expanded audience that they could go
deeper into some of the things that were
discussed was really really cool and a
huge recognition for us that the
community was going to be
an incredible part of what would make
react work and had at that point was
definitely already a really important
part of what had gotten react to that
point so far
[Music]
it's proven to me that uh engaging with
your open source Community is is
actually more important than the
technical work itself like if you don't
have a community you don't have an open
source project I'm excited that we just
continue rethinking best practices I
want to thank this community for making
it possible for us to keep investing in
this and keep working on it
um that's all I got thanks
it was a real high point for not just
for me but for the team and you know I
think for Facebook engineering I think
we really felt like
not just validated but like we were
actually like doing something that
people cared about
and it was a really really good feeling
it was already like more widely used
within the company but now it was like
okay how do we like actually start
converting everything to react how do we
like remove and deprecate like all of
the other Frameworks and really like
double down on react oh hey I was going
going from like an interesting product
to like this is the next big thing so it
was really like a really amazing time to
be around and to like really like get
the whole company like working together
as one uh you know to like make this
happen
let's see I have some keepsakes up here
which will be not easy for me to get
down but
let's see
I have some stickers oh this is a fun
one this is the first ever react die cut
sticker
we ordered like a bunch of these and put
them on our laptops and I just I never
wanted to use the last one that I had
Facebook open source stickers
oh some of these will be a trip down
memory lane for folks react conf we made
you know 2018
Facebook open source
it's a good one react conf attendee
badge
this was a book uh from the original
react.js conf at Facebook's headquarters
so this had a list of the speakers and
the schedule and
um here's the Keynote
and Christopher shadow
we had all sorts of
swag made and a bunch of other stuff so
pretty good stuff
pretty good memories
dated with questions from the community
and a new developer enters reacts orbit
[Music]
what should I do with my hands
so you're saying that I should actually
uh start like uh let me Focus for a
second just for the record I did not
create react react was created by Jordan
walk
I worked at a small startup we were
creating a sort of a digital publishing
platform so there was a really complex
post editor with different blocks or
like a scrollable text with like
different effects and stuff and so uh
creating a dynamic kind of interactive
editor for for these things was really
difficult and we returned it with
backbone I kind of wanted to give react
a try because it was supposed to solve
this problem
the first react component I wrote was a
like button so it was just like a button
you click it and it says like you like
this or you and somebody like this or
you and like 40 others like this so
there was a bit of like a split and
logic and then the way you would Express
this in uh like in other Frameworks at
the time uh like you had you had to kind
of manually like watch what's changed
and like update it and in react you
could just say if nobody liked this show
this if one person like this show this
otherwise show this and like it's a very
natural way to write this kind of code
and yeah I just wrote that button and I
was like yeah that looks good ship it
and so we actually rewrote the entire
app in react over the course of like 90
months while still shipping new features
so react speed up our development so
much that we were able to add new
features faster at the same time as we
were replacing old features that's why I
really kind of fell in love with it
a lot of things didn't exist back then
like there was no such thing as a react
ecosystem so if you needed something
it didn't exist you'd have to write it
so like you'd have to figure out how to
do it because otherwise you're not going
to have a product right so that's kind
of what I did for a bunch of things
one of those projects in particular was
uh
like I just saw like a big opportunity
there
it was called react hot loader at the
time so I wanted to give a talk about
that
somebody else has done a talk that
mentioned it earlier at reactant a
really clever fellow called Damn abramov
figured this out and he created the
react hotloader and I felt that well
then that just wouldn't be interesting
because people kind of already saw it
which in retrospect I don't think it
would be true but that's how I saw it at
the time so I wanted to kind of spice it
up a little bit and I wanted to make a
proof of concept of a thing I saw in
breath Victor's demo that is often
referred to as time traveling
you're designing something embedded in
time you need to be able to control time
you need to be able to see across time
otherwise you're designing blind
I didn't really know how to do it but I
thought that's a cool idea for a talk so
I'm gonna send the proposal if the
proposal is successful then I'll just
figure it out and it turned out that the
proposal was more successful than I
thought it would be and so I made a
proof of concept for that and that
approval concept became known as Redux
so my talk is about developer tools
because react and hotel ordering and
time travel these are all developer
tools he was like literally creating
Redux in service of being able to
deliver this this talk and I called it
presentation driven development because
the Thing That Shook out of it was you
know this sort of like canonical State
Management library for react apps for
for several years most of my work is
around the react ecosystem because
that's what inspired me to contribute to
the open source in the first place but
there are two particular projects that
I'm going to talk about today it was
very
validating to give that talk
but I was not surprised by
the response because well I I had my
doubts but also I thought the talk was
good like I thought it's a really good
talk
and I was glad that people also liked it
but I think it was actually not the talk
that was uh that was really like the
moment for me I think it was just like
being there
I kind of felt like you know like like
going to Hogwarts for the first time I
think it kind of had this uh this
feeling because there were all these
people who I only knew them as these
avatars and when I season meet somebody
in person they they kind of become
three-dimensional of course you kind of
see the whole picture and I think it was
just like such a wholesome feeling is
the feeling that we are all trying to
figure out what we can do with this
thing and we don't know it yet and we're
just playing with it
that's also where I met jinchan I asked
for for her advice before because she's
one of the co-creators of the fox
architecture so it was nice to meet her
in person and she mentioned that
actually Facebook is hiring in London
and so they arranged an interview for me
right at the conference which was like
our normal interview process the same I
think like four interviews or something
like this but I I missed the second day
of the conference but we just did an
interview there and so that's kind of
how I got into Facebook
we just quickly grabbed them out of the
conference a little bit like on the down
low and then uh conducted the interviews
um in the basement of a hotel I think is
that normal entries no Dan is so special
he's always been all special I guess
like I would think of myself as like
maybe the first
member of what would become the react
team as you know it today because I
joined a little bit earlier than I think
Andrew Brian Luna and and like a bunch
of other people who work with us now and
I joined at the time when a few people
who worked with us before were just
about to leave so I was kind of in this
transitional period when the team was
changing a lot
foreign
[Music]
do you remember the first time you met
Andrew
uh I think I've met
I think I met him yeah well that was the
clear moment maybe was that the first
time we actually did you get invited to
react conf because of that he had a
speech
I met him like I think before that I met
you and Sophie and Joe and Tim like all
in the same week yeah he started asking
some questions that were very similar to
the questions that on the team we were
talking about internally and so I just
remember like I gotta connect you with
like Sebastian and Jordan and the rest
of the team yeah and then also I was
like to the recruiters I was like yeah
this guy like we gotta hire this Andrew
guy and I think we were really fortunate
early on to have a bunch of people
liking that kind of stepped up and they
were like this seems cool I just want to
be a part of this I just want to help
I didn't realize it was kind of like a
freshman class sort of feeling at the
time
started managing the team around that
time as well
um and like I couldn't have really asked
for a better uh both project and like a
set of colleagues and team to to join
the beginning of phase two yeah that's
cool
[Music]
like man we're nailing this
react was now out of the hands of its
Founders it was ready to take on New
Life in the care of a new community
grown and future-minded team we tried to
watch some of the numbers like the
number of GitHub stars or the number of
npm downloads on Google Trends how many
people are searching for react and none
of those numbers are perfect but
basically all of them kept going up over
time and eventually got to a point where
we looked at it and said oh yeah like
millions of people essentially are using
react there are a lot of little details
in how we did things that encourages
an ecosystem to participate that were
critical Parts on making it what it is
today we didn't put everything in the
framework we left a lot of it to the
ecosystem to innovate and we got a lot
of contributions we got a lot of
interest that way we got a lot of things
spurring from that it was not ever a
foregone conclusion I like it's still
surreal to me that it's as popular as it
is it's this great example of this like
Underdog technology within a big company
where there could have been these forces
that really pushed back on it I think a
lot of elements of good timing Good
Fortune good luck good leadership
support all sort of like aggregated to
allow react to be a success that had we
missed a few of those or had a handful
more things failed instead of succeeded
then I do not think react would be in
the spot that it is today
I feel like you can't take anyone out of
it and have it be what it became I think
in the early days obviously Jordan right
like this thing wouldn't exist and then
Jing Chan just absolutely critical I
mean she was so instrumental in the
early days of react that it just
wouldn't have been a thing that we cared
about if it didn't prove itself
and then Shane O'Sullivan is responsible
for you know really I mean a very hard
decision to like I'm gonna go this path
instead of that thing and then the
engineers that worked on refining and
iterating on it and turning it into
something good it was Chateau and Paul
shantacy and Pete hunt and my manager
Adam wolf when I was like you know
asking all these questions about like
should we be do like is this even worth
it especially after JS conf when we were
feeling defeated you know he was there
to pick me back up and be like no look
it is delivering value this is good keep
going and there's different phases too
right you have the early early days and
you had the like for the next literally
almost we're going on 10 years now with
Sebastian's technical leadership and
Andrew and Dan and Dominic and flarney
and Sophie and I I just feel like it's
just a group of incredible people and if
you take any of them out of it
it just looks pretty different it was
really a team effort
uh it was really a team effort from the
very beginning
[Music]
says that awesome Solutions are rarely
created by large organizations it's
almost always one person with passion
and vision that slowly start to infect
others this is this is a great summary
of how react became react because it was
never inevitable it was always this wild
idea that kept Gathering momentum person
by person and any expected react to fail
and if it weren't for the hard work of a
few determined developers it very well
could have
this is just the beginning of the react
story the story of how a community
transformed an underdog UI Library into
the most popular JavaScript framework
today
this is react podcast I'm fantastic
[Music]
thank you
I'm like so tempted to just
prize FaceTime Jordan right now be like
interview it's just really strange to
think that
you're just so close to death the first
reactive shirt that we made
thousands of developers find jobs across
Europe using Honeypot if you're up for a
new challenge in one of these European
cities sign up at honeypot.io
if you want to see more Tech
documentaries then subscribe so you
don't miss the next one
[Music]